我们现在考虑一个稍微复杂的例子;这是一个三连杆平面机器人。
Let's now consider a slightly more complex example; this is a three link planar robot.
你会记得关于正向运动学的讲座，一个有三个关节的机器人
As you will remember from the lecture about forward kinematics, a robot with three joints
或三个自由度，允许我们控制末端效应器的姿势，而不仅仅是它
or three degrees of freedom, allows us to control the end effector pose, not just its
位置，它是X，它是Y，但也是末端效应器的方向。
position, it's X and it's Y, but also the orientation of the end effector.
我们将标记这个机器人的链接长度，我们将指出关节
We're going to label the link lengths of this robot and we're going to indicate the joint
角度，Q1，Q2和Q3。我们将指出包含X的末端效应器姿势
angles, Q1, Q2, and Q3. We're going to indicate the end effector pose which comprises an X
和Y分量和方向θ。我们之前已经描述了如何写下来
and a Y component and an orientation theta. We've previously described how to write down
用二维齐次变换表示末端执行器姿态的表达式
an expression for the pose of the end effector in terms of two dimensional homogeneous transformations
它是一个转换链，绕Q1旋转，沿着链接平移
and it is a chain of transformations, rotation about Q1, translation along the link by an
量A1，绕Q2旋转，沿第二连杆平移到A2的距离，
amount A1, rotation about Q2, translation along the second link by a distance to A2,
通过连接角度3旋转，然后沿链节3平移距离A3。它的
rotation by join angle three and then a translation along link three by the distance A3. It's
有点繁琐，但相对简单地将所有矩阵相乘
a little bit tedious but relatively straightforward to multiply all of the matrices together and
我最终得到了一个均匀的变换矩阵，它代表了机器人的姿势
I end up with a homogeneous transformation matrix, which represents the pose of the robot
末端效应器，这是一个三维，均匀的变换矩阵，二维。
end effector and this is a three by three, homogeneous transformation matrix, in two dimensions.
您会记得，矩阵的某些部分代表了平移
You will recall that there are some parts of the matrix which represent the translational
姿势的组成部分，矩阵的其他部分代表旋转
component of the pose and there are other parts of the matrix which represent the rotational
姿势的一部分。让我们首先看一下这两个元素的翻译部分
part of the pose. Let's look first at the translational part that is these are two elements
在这里的矩阵中，我可以将它们拉出来，它们代表X和Y坐标
in the matrix up here and I can pull those out and they represent the X and Y co-ordinate
末端效应器的姿势。
of the end effector pose.
相对于时间和我们的计算，计算这些衍生物相对简单
It's relatively simple to compute the derivate of these with respect to time and as we did
之前，我可以用矩阵形式写这个，所以我们有一个X点和Y点的表达式，
earlier, I can write this in matrix form, so we have an expression for X dot and Y dot,
就雅可比矩阵而言，这次我们的雅可比矩阵有两行和三行
in terms of a Jacobian Matrix and this time our Jacobian Matrix has got two rows and three
列和它乘以关节角速度矢量Q1点，Q2点
columns and that is multiplied by a vector of joint angle velocities, Q1 dot, Q2 dot
和Q3点。这非常简单。现在让我们看看旋转部分和
and Q3 dot. This is pretty straightforward. Let's look now at the rotational part and
我要把它拉出来。这是我们姿势的旋转部分，描述了方向
I'm going to pull that out. This is the rotational part of our pose, describes the orientation
机器人末端执行器
of the robot end effector.
我们很早就知道了二维旋转矩阵的一般形式
We learnt very early on that the general form for a rotation matrix in two dimensions looks
像这样。通过将cos符号和sin函数的参数等同于此，它非常漂亮
like this. By equating the arguments of the cos sign and sin functions here, it's pretty
明确我们可以为theta写这个等于Q1加Q2加Q3。
clear that we can write this for theta is equal to Q1 plus Q2 plus Q3.
如果你考虑问题的几何形状，那么这个结果实际上并不是特别的
If you think about the geometry of the problem then this result is actually not particularly
奇怪。现在我可以考虑时间的θ的导数，所以Q点是
surprising. Now I can take the derivative of theta with respect to time, so Q dot is
等于Q1点，再加上Q2点，再加上Q3点，我再次将其分解并以矩阵形式写入。
equal to Q1 dot, plus Q2 dot, plus Q3 dot and once again I can factorize this and write it in matrix form.
这是X点和Y点的表达式，这里是theta点的表达式。
Here is the expression for X dot and Y dot and here is the expression for theta dot.
现在它们都是矩阵乘以关节角速度的矢量。我可以
Now both of them are a matrix multiplied by a vector of joint angle velocities. I can
将这些组合在一起基本上我堆叠了两个矩阵，最后我得到了雅可比矩阵
combine these together basically I stack two matrices and I end up with a Jacobian Matrix
这是三乘三。在这里我有联合速度，在这里我有空间
which is three by three. Here I have the joint velocity and over here I have the spatial
机器人末端执行器的速度，但关节之间再次呈线性关系
velocity of the robot end effector, but once again a linear relationship between joint
末端执行器的速度和空间速度。
velocity and spatial velocity of the end effector.
因此对于这三个链接，具有关节角度Q1，Q2和Q3的平面机械手，我可以定义
So for this three link, planar manipulator with joint angles Q1, Q2 and Q3, I can define
和它的平移速度相关的末端效应器速度，就是它的X点
and end effector velocity in terms of its translational velocity, that's it's X dot
和Y点分量以及它的旋转速度;thetadot。所以，如果我指定
and Y dot component and also in terms of its rotational velocity; theta dot. So if I specify
那就是我想要的特殊机器人控制问题，然后计算
that, that’s what I want in my particular robot control problem, then computing the
Jacobian并采用它的逆，我可以计算出我需要的关节角度的速度
Jacobian and taking its inverse, I can compute the velocity of the joint angles that I need
为了达到最终效应器的速度。
in order to achieve that end effector velocity.